Guide to the Heman Lincoln Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Heman Lincoln papers
1838-1887
RG 290
Yale University Divinity School Library
5
(12 boxes)
The Heman Lincoln Papers primarily document the professional work of Lincoln as a Baptist minister and professor at Newton Theological Institution.
Lincoln, Heman, 1821-1887
Biographical / Historical
Chronology
1821 April 14 Born in Boston, MA
1840 Graduated from Brown University
1840-1842 Principal, Academy at Derby, VT
1845 Received certificate, Newton Theological Institution
1845 September 21 Ordained (Baptist), Boston, MA
1845-1850 Minister, New Britain Baptist Church, PA
1848-1853 Editor, Christian Chronicle
1850-1853 Minister, Franklin Square Baptist Church, Philadelphia, PA
1853-1859 Minister, First Baptist Church, Jamaica Plain, MA
1854-1867 Editor, Watchman and Reflector
1860-1868 Minister, Central Baptist Church, Providence, RI
1868-1873 Professor, Church History, Newton Theological Institution
1873-1878 Professor, Homiletics, Pastoral Duties and Church Polity, Newton Theological Institution
1878-1887 Professor, Church History, NTI
1887 October 18 Died, Newton Centre, MA
Conditions Governing Access
Collection open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Heman Lincoln Papers, 1838-1887, primarily document the professional work of Lincoln. The collection is arranged according to the following categories: diaries, letters, lectures and essays, sermons, student lecture notes, and notes on readings, miscellaneous papers. The miscellaneous material includes data related to Lincoln's pastorates and scrapbooks of clippings related to Baptist churches in general. The bulk of the collection consists of sermons, including 215 undated sermons and dated sermons from 1838-1880.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
From the Andover Newton Theological School collection, transferred in 2017
Arrangement
Arranged in seven series: I. Diaries.
II. Letters.
III. Lectures and Essays.
IV. Sermons.
V. Student Lecture Notes.
VI. Notes on Readings.
VII. Miscellaneous Papers
Baptists -- New England; Baptists -- Clergy; Lincoln, Heman, 1821-1887; Newton Theological Institution
- Diaries, Series I
  - Diary entries, 1846 (Box 1)
  - Lists of readings, expenditures, 1854 (Box 1)
  - Lists of readings, some diary entries, 1860 (Box 1)
  - Diary entries, expenditures, 1866 (Box 1)
  - Diary entries, expenditures, 1876 (Box 1)
- Letters, Series II
  Scope and Contents
  Includes letters and writings of Peter Johnson, Robert, Orramel, Francis H. T., Francis A. S., Annie, and Emily Gulick
  - Henry Blanchard to HL; from Dorchester, MA, No date (Box 2)
  - Irah Chase to HL; from Newton Centre, MA, 1863 April 6 (Box 2)
  - Eben Dodge to HL; from Hamilton, NY, 1867 December 30 (Box 2)
  - HL to [S. L. Caldwell]; from Brooklyn, NY, 1876 June 10 (Box 2)
  - Wm. C. Strong to HL; from Newton Centre, MA, 1879 December 5 (Box 2)
  - Alva Woods to HL; from ·Providence, RI, 1879 December 17 (Box 2)
  - Robert G. Seymour to HL, from Boston, MA., 1884 November 30 (Box 2)
  - D. Lothrop Co. to HL; from Boston, MA, 1887 (Box 2)
  - John J. Bulfinch to HL;·from Waldoboro, ME, 1887 May 24 (Box 2)
  - Thomas S. Samson to HL; from New Haven, CT., 1885 June 22 (Box 2)
- Lectures and Essays, Series III
  - Undated fragments (8 folders) (Box 2)
  - Untitled lectures and essays (13 folders) (Box 2)
  - Address at Central (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The antiquity of man (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Apologetics (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Article from the "Studien and Krihten"? by George Funk (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The atmosphere a seed-bag (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Baptist history (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Baptists in the United States (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The broken pitcher (from the German of Tochokke) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Charge to Rev. Mr. Barrow - Neponset, May 30/1855 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Christian value of Kings + Chronicles (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Christmas Talk (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - A Church Polity in the New Testament (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Comparative Religions (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Confirmations of the Doctrine of Future Retribution from the Higher Thought of the Age (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Continuation of the Sketch of … theologians (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Conversion of Saul of Tarsus (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Council of Constance (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Development Theory in relation to Christian Theology (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Does the Bible teach the restoration of the Jews to Palestine as a nation? (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Educational Needs (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Egypt's Place in the World's History (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Exegesis--June 21/1847 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - The Half-Way Covenant (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - History of Civilization in England. By Henry Thomas Buck (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - How far is love to God disinterested? (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Ideals of Life (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Infant Membership (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Influence of Piety and Success (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Is National Morality Declining (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - General Lecture on Parables (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - The Gallican Church (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Gregory the Great (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Growth of Religion in the United States (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - John Bunyan (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Kahn on the Attributes (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Keep sacred day, when sanctuary open for worship (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Layard's Discoveries at Nineveh (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Lecture at New Britain, March 1, 1849 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Lectures on Astronomy (1848) (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Leo the Great (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Life of Martin Luther (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Lineborch (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Mahommedanism: Its Character and the sources of its power (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Many are awakened, without conversion (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Many are thoughtful + serious, wt. becoming Xns. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Memoir of Oberlin (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Mental Culture (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous scraps for miscellaneous reading for miscellaneous purposes (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Missionary Talk (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Missions in the Nineteenth Century (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - The Montanists (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - The Monuments of Egypt in their Chronological + Ethnological Relations (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - The Number who need the Gospel (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - New England Theology (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Object and Aims of the Horticultural Society (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Origin of evil. Tholuck (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - The Pastoral Office (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Plenary Inspiration (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - The Poetry of Mrs. Heman (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Pre-Millennial Reign (3 items) (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Queenstadt on Eternity (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Reinhard's Plan (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Religious Condition of Germany (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Religious Life in England under the Commonwealth (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Review of Darwin's Origin of Species. 8 Oct. 1860 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - The Rise and Growth of the Papacy (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Sanctification (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Science not supreme but subordinate (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Science not supreme but subordinate (2nd draft) (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Scottish School (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - A Sermon (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Sermon by I. S. Buckminster (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Sermon of Henry Melvill (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Sin by commandment appear exceeding sinful (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Spiritual power of Apostolic churches, compared with those of modern times (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Start from God--of Him--thru Him--to Him (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Tendencies and Duties of Baptists (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - "Testimony of the Rocks" by Hugh Miller (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - The Turanian Religions (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Turretin--Book 13. Locus 6--Sec. 13 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - The Ultimate Success of the Missionary Enterprise (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - What Can be done for non Church goers? (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Will the Jews return, as a nation to Palestine? (Box 4, Folder 42)
- Sermons, Series III
  For a full listing of sermon texts see the orginal finding aid available at repository.
  - Chronological listing of sermons preached from 2 March 1852 to 6 December, 1885. (two volumes) Each volume also contains a listing of weddings performed during the period covered. (Box 5)
  - Undated sermons arranged by text: Genesis - Galatians (Box 5)
  - Undated sermons arranged by text: Ephesians - Revelations (Box 6)
  - Dated sermons, 1838, 1842-1852 February (Box 6)
  - Dated sermons, 1852 March - 1855 (Box 7)
  - Dated sermons, 1856–1860 (Box 8)
  - Dated sermons, 1861–1864 (Box 9)
  - Dated sermons, 1865-1868 March (Box 10)
  - Dated sermons, 1868 April - 1869, 1871, 1872, 1877, 1878, 1880 (Box 11)
- Student Lecture Notes, Series V
  Notes taken while a student at Newton Theological Institution, arranged by professor of course
  - Hackett, Horatio. Translation from the Old Testament (Box 11)
  - Ripley, Henry J. Lectures on Pastoral Duties (Box 11)
  - [Ripley, Henry J.] Lectures on Sacred Rhetoric (Box 11)
  - Sears, Barnas. Lectures on Systematic Theology (Box 11)
- Notes on Readings, Series VI
  - Lists of articles and books (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - Notebook: Books for one's Library (Box 11)
  - Notebook--List of Contributions to Watchman, Youth's Companion, etc. (Box 11)
  - Two untitled notebooks of notes on readings (Box 11)
  - Notebook--Common-place book of Reflections and Opinions. (Box 11)
  - Notebook: Scrap-Book of Choice Quotations collected at Sundry times and in divers manners by Heman Lincoln jr. (Box 11)
  - Notebook: Scraps for Illustration, etc. (Box 12)
  - Subjects in Church History (1 folder) (Box 12)
- Miscellaneous Papers, Series VII
  - Personal papers
    - Account books (two volumes, mostly blank) (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous papers, one unidentified photograph (1 folder) (Box 12)
  - Papers related to Lincoln's former churches
    - List of members, miscellaneous papers (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - List of members (one volume, church not identified) (Box 12)
    - Lists of pastoral visits ( three volumes) (Box 12)
  - Various
    - Delegates and visitors to "American Missionary Union" 1862. Entertained by Brown Street Baptist Church and Society. Tuesday May 27 to Friday 30th 1862 (one volume) (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous papers (1 folder) (Box 12)
    - Scrapbooks of newspaper articles--mostly dealing with Baptist churches (two volumes) (Box 12–13)